Guide to the Mark Solomon and Robert Kaufman Research Files on African Americans and Communism TAM.218
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Mark Solomon and Robert Kaufman Research Files on African Americans and Communism
1919-2017
1919-1939
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Solomon, Mark I.
TAM.218
4.75 Linear Feet in 4 record cartons, 1 manuscript box and 1 half manuscript box.
The collection is comprised of research materials regarding African Americans and communism accumulated by two scholars: Mark Solomon and Robert Kaufman. It contains clippings, articles, printed ephemera, internal documents, published documents (principally from radical organizations), research notes, and government surveillance documents.
Arrangement
The files are grouped into two series: I, Mark Solomon Research Files; II, Robert Kaufman Research Files. Folders in original donation are arranged alphabetically. Materials from the 2019 accretion were added into Series I boxes five and six and have not been arranged by an archivist. The materials in the 2019 accretion are arranged in the order in which they were received from the donor.
Biographical Note
Mark Solomon is the author of The Cry Was Unity: Communists and African Americans, 1917-1936(1988). He taught U.S. history at Simmons College from 1967 to 1997. The Robert Kaufman created/accumulated his portion of this collection during research at the University of California, Berkeley on his (never completed) doctoral thesis on African American labor and communism.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Mark Solomon in 2000; an additional accession was donated by Mark Solomon in 2018. The accession numbers associated with these gifts are 2000.008 and 2019.042.
Scope and Contents
The collection is comprised of research materials regarding African Americans and communism accumulated by two scholars: Mark Solomon and Robert Kaufman. In 1998, Solomon wrote The Cry Was Unity: Communists and African Americans, 1917-1936 and his research files for this book are included in this collection. Research files from Robert Kaufman's dissertation are also included in this collection. Materials include clippings, printed ephemera, internal and published documents, principally from radical organizations, research notes, and some government documents (surveillance of radicals).
Additionally, there are well-documented notes and correspondence between Mark Solomon and committee members of the Organization of American Historians such as Nell Painter.
Government records; Notes.; Drafts (documents); Printed ephemera.; African American labor union members -- History; African Americans -- Politics and government.; Clippings (information artifacts); Communism -- United States -- History.; Labor unions and communism -- United States.; African American communists -- History; Correspondence.; Kaufman, Robert; Painter, Nell Irvin; Organization of American Historians
- Series I. Mark Solomon Research Files
  - African Blood Brotherhood, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - African-American Press - notes & clippings, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - African-American Press - notes & clippings, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Allen, James S. - Negro Liberation, 1933-1938 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - American Negro Labor Committee, 1924-1930s (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Anti-lynch movement and activities, 1933-1938 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Articles, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Articles, 1966-1996 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Biographies-Bibliographies, undated, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Black nationalism (& CP), 1931-1934 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Black response to Communism, 1921-1973 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Black organizations, 1934-1938 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Blacks and Soviet Russia, 1922-1988 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Bonus March veterans, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Business ideologies (co-ops), 1931-1966 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Briggs correspondence - Intelligence File, 1958-1961 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Chicago - unemployment and eviction, 1931-1944 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Comintern, 1920s-1993 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Communist Party, 1929-1931 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Communist Party, 1931-1933 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Communist Party, 1933-1936 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Communist Party and black organizations, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Communist Party - gestation, 1918-1974 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Communist Party - South, 1932-1967 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Conference: Rosenwal conference on the economic situation of the Negro, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Correspondence, 1974-1976 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - The Crusader notes, summaries of 1919/1920s edition, undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Culture, 1929-1991 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Draper Papers - Emory University, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Economic conditions, 1929-1934 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Elections (& CP), 1932-1934 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Ethiopia - imperialism, war, Fascism, 1928-1936 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Garveyism & Communism, 1923-1952 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Government investigations, ca.1919-1931 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Government investigations files & notes, 1920s-1930s (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Government investigations, 1920-1930 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Harlem riot, 1933-1936 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Herndon, Angelo, 1933-1976 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Huiswoud, Otto - biography, 1929-1998 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Inprecorr, 1928-1935 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - International TU community of Negro Workers (ITUCNW), 1933-1937 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - International Labor Defense (ILD), 1929-1936 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Interviews - notes, research material, 1970s (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Labor issues, 1931-1936 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - League of Struggle for Negro Rights (LSNR), ca.1933 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Left - pre-Communist - notes, typescripts, 1931-1936 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Lynching photocopies, notes, 1931-1935 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - McKay, Claude, ca.1924-1930 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Minor, Robert notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - NAACP and Scottsboro - newspaper clippings, notes, ca.1931 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - NAACP (The Crisis) booklet, notes, newspaper clippings, ca.1934 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - National Negro Congress, 1935-1938 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - The Negro Liberator - notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - New Deal, 1932-1937 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - New Masses and other cultural material, 1930-1935 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Padmore and ITUCNW, 1933-1935 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Popular Front (policies and action), 1935-1955 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Scottsboro trial - newspaper clippings, research notes, 1928-1933 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Scottsboro trial - newspaper clippings, research notes, 1934-1977 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Self-determination - "Nation within a Nation", 1927-1993 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Sharecroppers - Alabama, 1930-1976 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Sharecroppers' Union repression South, 1929-1940 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - South - Gastonia etc., 1929-1967 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Students and youth, 1932-1934 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Trade Union Unity League Unions (TUUL), 1927-1973 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Trade Unions (CIO), 1935-1936 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Unemployed Movement (UCs), 1931-1935 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - White Chauvinism and CP, 1933-1935 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Assorted research material, 1936-2013 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Hobsbawm Review, 2011 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Notes and papers, 1978-2007 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - OAH 78 proposal "Marxism and Black History", 1977-1979 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Berrons Commission on Interracial Cooperation, 1934-1940 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Articles and newspaper clippings, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, grants and fellowships, 1973-1974 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Research materials, 1945-1950 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - (Negro) Ideology - War, Imperialism - Facism, 1933-1938 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - August 1931 Chicago anti-eviction mvt (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - NAACP- org and ideologies, 1936-1941, 1931-1941 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - The South - mvt and conditions, 1937 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - NAACP- ideology and tactics, 1929-1936, 1934-1938 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Research to be sorted, 1934-1938 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Organizations - Negro Urban League, etc, 1932 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Cultural movement (Negro and White), 1933-1934 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Institutions - Negro colleges +(women), 1933-1936 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Politics - Parties Ideology, 1934-1940 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Conditions - Negro, general, 1933 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Communist party and the Negro movement, 1931 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Organized labor and the Negro, 1934-1936 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Rosenwald Fund Conference, 1933 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Interracial movement and cooperation, 1933-1941 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Contact interview lists, 1973-1974 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - The student movement and youth movement, 1933-1940 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Spain and Negro, 1936 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Religious movement, 1937-1965 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Ideology - Negro strategy and tactics, 1934-1937 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Chas. Martin - AHA Proposal, 1976-1977 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Research materials, 1970-1973 (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Lectures and drafts, 1976-2017 (Box 5, Folder 31-32)
  - "R", 1974 (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Promotional materials for The Cry Was Unity, 1999 (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Research notes and publications, 1947-2017 (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - Ancillary materials, The Cry Was Unity, 1999-2000 (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - Post-1936 - CP, etc., 1936-1945 (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - Research materials, 1937 (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - Kaufman miscellaneous, 1827-1937 (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - Articles and notes, 1933-1987 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Cold War critics, 1941-1969 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Materials, Black Cold War critics, 1946-1971 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Papers and drafts, 1977-1979 (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Series II. Robert Kaufman Research Files
  - African Blood Brotherhood, 1921-1974 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - American Negro Labor Congress (ANLC), 1924-1929 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Bibliographies, ca.1939, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Black business, 1920-1940 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Black Leadership, 1921-1924 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Brotherhood of Sleeping Car Porters, 1919-1934 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Camp Hill, undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Chicago eviction riot - newspaper clippings, 1931-1933 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Communist Party, 1924-1925 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Communist Party, 1928-1935 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Communist Party - Report on economic crisis for 13th Plenum CPUSA (typescript 41 pp.), 1931 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Conference, Second Amenia, Aug 18, 1933-Aug 21, 1923 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Coolidge - black attitude, undated (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Crosswaith, Frank - articles, 1928-1941 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Du Bois - articles, 1928-1934 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Duvall, C.H., "The Building of a Race" (lecture, 62 pp.), 1919 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Ford, James W., "World Problems of the Negro People" (pamphlet, 23 pp.), undated (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Fortyninth State Movement, 1934 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Gastonia, 1929 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Gordon, Eugene - columns, 1933-1934 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Harlem - letter, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Harper, Solomon, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Harrison, Hubert - articles, 1912-1927 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Houston, Charles - letter, 1934 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Imperialism, Congress against, ca.1931 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Johnson, Charles S., "The Economic Status of Negroes"(pamphlet, 53 pp.), 1919 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Labor Age, 1931-1967 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Labor struggles, 1924-1934 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - League of Struggle for Negro Rights, 1933-1942 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Lynching and anti-lynch, 1929-1934 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Migration, 1923-1944 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - NAACP - correspondence research notes, 1931-1938 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - National Association of Wage Earners - domestic workers, ca.1924 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - National Unemployment League, undated (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Needle Trade Workers, 1931-1932 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Nowlin, William, "The Negro in American National Politics", 1931 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - O'Neil, Socrate Abelard E., "Negro Problem Solved" (pamphlet, 61 pp.), 1918 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Pickens, William, 1932 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Powell, Adam Clayton Sr., ca.1932 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Press clippings - African American, 1931 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Press items from tape (typescripts), undated (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Scottsboro - correspondence (research notes), 1931-1934 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Scottsboro-newspaper clippings, 1931-1933 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Sharecroppers - letter, 1942 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Socialist Party, 1934 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Stool Pigeon testimony - William Nowell and Manning Johnson, 1951 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Unemployment, 1931-1932 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - UNIA, 1926-1939 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Urban conditions - Detroit and Baltimore, 1927-1935 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Vaughn, Geo L., "The Negro Armageddon" (pamphlet, 28 pp.), ca.1925 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Walrond, Eric D., includes article on Caspar Holstein, 1927-1935 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Walton, Lester A., undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Women workers, 1932 (Box 4, Folder 12)